

Washington, DC | paulfranz@gmail.com | linkedin.com/in/pkfranz | www.paul-franz.com

## Summary

# Director of Digital and Content Strategy | Visual Corporate Storytelling

Merging Technology and Storytelling to Drive Organizational Results and Impact

Tech-savvy, strategic digital communications leader expert in directing and creating content that uses the best video, photography, and data visualization to clearly communicate complex concepts. Award-winning multimedia producer with deep IT *and* editorial expertise. In-demand presenter on storytelling and integrated creative and technical teams.

#### Career Highlights

- \* Expanded think-tank's visibility by producing cutting-edge visual and digital content easily accessible to millions.
- \* Won industry-leading award for Best Data Visualization—besting competition from Uber, Google, and NBC.
- \* Headline speaker on visual storytelling with maps at Mapbox's 2019 GovSummit conference
- \* Creative team leader: Built staff of 2 into an integrated 90 percent female team of 15 technical and creative pros.

#### Areas of Expertise

- \* Digital Editorial-Content Strategy | Visual Storytelling | Strategic Communications | Project Management | Business Insights \* Team Building | Multimedia Production | Creative Team Leadership
- \* Adobe Creative Suite | Marketing | Analytics | Web Development | Public Speaking | Vendor Management | Budgeting

# **Experience**

CENTER FOR STRATEGIC AND INTERNATIONAL STUDIES (CSIS) | Washington, DC | 2012— PRESENT Global affairs policy think tank providing analysis to government and private sector. CSIS employs a staff of more than 250 full-time staff and had an operating revenue of more than \$44 million in 2018.

**Director of Technology/Dracopoulos Chair in Creativity and Innovation**, 2016–present | Director of Multimedia (2013–2016) | Multimedia Producer (2012–2013)

Develop ideas and **oversee production of innovative digital communications projects** to create and distribute visually engaging and interactive content accessible for broad audiences. Collaborate with CSIS research program directors and other subject matter experts to implement effective outreach strategies using new forms of media and interactivity. Educate university students on digital storytelling in CSIS's Journalism Boot Camp program. Evangelize and present on CSIS digital program as sought-after public speaker. Lead creative and technical mentor to staff of 15 full-time producers, developers, designers, and interns. Operating budget in 2018 was more than \$1 million.

- \* **Digital and Visual Storytelling**. Partnered with chief communications officer to transform traditional newsroom into innovative production studio of award-winning integrated, visual, and interactive digital content.
- --Introduced video explainers, podcasts, issue-focus websites, data visualizations, motion graphics, and animation to move organization beyond print and Power Point-based content.
- --Grew department from 2 video producers into diverse 90 percent female multidisciplinary team of 15 designers, web developers, audio/video producers, and data scientists to ensure creative and technical excellence.
- --Secured \$5M endowment to create first non-academic chair to expand funding for digital storytelling projects.
- \* Interactive Issue-Focused Websites. Instituted customized, project-focused microsites to detail research programs using easy-to-understand interactive data visualizations, expanding visibility and funding opportunities.
- --Garnered world news coverage from CNN, NYT, and others as a result of report from microsite for Asia Maritime Transparency Initiative on secret Chinese bases in the South China Sea, which led to a U.S.-China summit.
- --Received industry Shorty Award for microsite featuring interactive world map graphing number and location of terrorist attacks over several years, which generated more than 1M views.
- \* Digital Enterprise Story | Video. Partnered with former PBS Newshour editor and CSIS Global Health Policy Center VP to art direct and edit <a href="CSIS's first-ever full-length video documentary">CSIS's first-ever full-length video documentary</a>, which aired nationally on PBS. The 60-minute film documented violence against medical humanitarians and continues to be featured at universities and health symposia.
- --Earned 2 "Awards of Excellence" from Impact Docs Awards international film competition.
- --Named an "Official Selection" in Doctors Without Borders Film Festival competition.

### EDITORIAL PROJECTS IN EDUCATION | Bethesda, MD | 2011–2012

Publisher of Education Week, online and print publication reporting on K-12 domestic policy issues.

### **Multimedia Producer and Reporter**

On daily basis, identified stories with potential for digital components, including video or interactive data visualizations. Educated print reporters on video reporting to expand reach.

- \* Introduced internal video and web-based reporting and debuted motion graphic-driven stories and reporting.
- \* Designed and produced video coverage of the 2012 presidential election.

### TIME INC | New York, NY | 2011

National newsweekly magazine and website with 2M+ subscribers.

#### **Video Journalist**

Member of TIME magazine's video production division. Wrote and executed on scripts involving staff and interviewees.

\* Produced capstone project on electric vehicles and future impact on the automotive industry.

### PULITZER CENTER ON CRISIS REPORTING | 2009–2011

Awards grants to support independent international reporting in underreported areas of the world.

# **Reporting Fellow and Pulitzer Grantee**

Awarded \$10,000 to complete self-selected reporting project, *Haiti's Lost Children*, on migrant farmers from Haiti in southern Florida. Organized series of reporting trips to Haiti after devastating earthquake in 2010. Directed 3 video stories, built website reporting on impact on Haiti's school system.

- \* Selected as 1 of only 5 grand prize winners out of 1000+ applicants.
- \* Received numerous honors including top honors for Best Video Project and was named a finalist for Best in Multimedia by prestigious Online News Association.

# LANCASTER NEWSPAPERS INC | Lancaster, PA | 2007–2009

Publisher of daily weekday and weekend newspapers and online news website.

# Reporter

Daily general assignment/crime and court reporter for small market daily and weekly newspaper. Shaped vision for the newspaper's online video and content strategies.

# **Awards**

#### **Shorty Awards** | Best in Data Visualization

Consortium of Universities for Global Health | Best Video in Global Health Advocacy

Online News Association | Best Website for Online Video Journalism | Best Multimedia Feature Website (Finalist) Best Online Video Site (Student, Co-Winner)

National Press Club | Joan Friedenberg Award for Online Journalism | Best in Multimedia Storytelling

### **Education**

M.A., Multimedia Journalism | University of Miami, Florida

B.A., Political Science and History (dual major) | Millersville University